<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the lamentable accidents caused by the inundation and rising of Ebro, Lobregat, Cinca and Segre riuers of Spaine together with a narration of a fearefull storme, which happened the third of Nouember, in the yeare 1617 in the hauen and port of Barcelona / written originally in Spanish by V. Rejaule the Kings aduocate ;  printed by authoritie at Valentia ; and now translated into English.</title>
            <author>Rejaule, V.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10587</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20860.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4850</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23961072</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23961072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27027</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10587)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27027)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1839:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the lamentable accidents caused by the inundation and rising of Ebro, Lobregat, Cinca and Segre riuers of Spaine together with a narration of a fearefull storme, which happened the third of Nouember, in the yeare 1617 in the hauen and port of Barcelona / written originally in Spanish by V. Rejaule the Kings aduocate ;  printed by authoritie at Valentia ; and now translated into English.</title>
                  <author>Rejaule, V.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Blackwall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Added illustrated t.p., with title: Newes from Spain.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spain --  History --  Philip III, 1598-1621.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27027:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEVVES FROM SPAIN</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>catastrophic flood in Span</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for WILLIAM BLACKVVALL, and are to be ſold his ſhop over againſt Guild-hall gate. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27027:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27027:2"/>
            <p>A TRVE RELATION OF THE LAMENTABLE Accidents, cauſed by the Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and riſing of <hi>Ebro, Lobregat, Cinca</hi> and <hi>Segre,</hi> Riuers of <hi>SPAINE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with</hi> A Narration of a fearefull Storme, which happened the third of <hi>Nouember,</hi> in the yeare 1617. in the Hauen and Port of BARCELONA.</p>
            <p>Written originally in Spaniſh by <hi>V. Rejaule</hi> the <hi>Kings Aduocate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by Authoritie at <hi>Valentia,</hi> and now Tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for WILLIAM BLACKVVALL. 1618.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27027:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27027:3"/>
            <head>NEWES FROM <hi>SPAINE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it be true (as it is infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible) that the Lord our God, before hee chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs rigorouſly, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, vſeth to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs, and giue vs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny warnings, that ſo wee might ceaſe to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and prouoke him: it is then a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſigne, that when the warnings (which God giues) are great and fearefull, that then our ſinnes are very great and haynous, and conſequently the chaſtiſement which wee deſerue for them, muſt needes be great and terrible. Among many other warnings in this latter age, one of the greateſt hath
<pb facs="tcp:27027:4"/>
beene the ſtrange inundations which of late haue happened in the Riuers of <hi>Ebro, Lobre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, Segre, Cinca,</hi> and other Streames iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and branching from them; the diſcourſe whereof, though it be ſhort, and would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect more being ſeene then related, yet the ryſing and ſwelling of theſe waters, being ſo ſtrange and notable, the particulers ſo certaine, and the loſſes proceeding thence ſo lamentable, I haue thought it not amiſſe to ſet them downe in writing.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>catastrophic flood in Span</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>But that which affrighted moſt, and cauſed the greateſt terrour to all men, was, when the Riuer of <hi>Ebro</hi> beganne to riſe, in ſuch ſort, that the Inhabitants of <hi>Tortoſa</hi> beganne to feare that it would carry away their Citie. For now at the beginning of its riſing, (which was about the ſhutting in of the day) that which the Riuer had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſet afloat, as cheſts, doores, beds, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, ſtooles, and infinite other things, did euidently ſhew the lamentable ſpoyle it had made vpon the bankes where the Riuer had paſſed.</p>
            <p>Which they of <hi>Tortoſa</hi> ſeeing, after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Proceſſions, Prayers, Letanies,<note n="a" place="margin">Rather ſhold you haue fixed the eye of your Faith &amp; Hope vpon Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the right hand of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> at laſt they opened the moſt holy Sacrament in their Churches, crying all for mercy to the diuine Maieſtie, deſiring that hee would be
<pb facs="tcp:27027:5"/>
pleaſed to pardon them, and to deliuer them from ſo euident and certaine a danger. The riſing of this Riuer continued two whole dayes, carrying away the Bridge of <hi>Torto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa,</hi> and guſhing into the Citie, caſt downe and carryed away more then an hundred houſes. It is impoſſible to relate the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular damages and ſpoyle of houſes, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and other grounds which ſtood on the bankes, beſides the death of Cattell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, there was one Country-man which had his houſe and three hundred Oliue trees, together with many other trees of ſundry other kindes carryed away with this violent and mercileſſe ſtreame: neyther was there one tree left ſtanding on the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſide.</p>
            <p>About ſome three leagues from the City of <hi>Tortoſa</hi> was a ſmall village called <hi>Beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallet,</hi> whereafter that the floud had drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned many of the Countrey people, which to ſaue their goods did hazard their liues, at laſt it carryed away the whole Towne, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:27027:6"/>
that of two hundred houſes there were left but onely ſixteene.</p>
            <p>In another little village called <hi>Gerta,</hi> about two leagues from <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> of two hundred and fifty houſes there remayned but onely ſeauen.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Gineſtar</hi> alſo, which ſtands about fiue leagues from <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> haue happened ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notable and lamentable loſſes, both in the houſes and in the fields. In briefe, ſo many and ſo great haue beene the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes all about the Riuer, that in all the places neare adioyning vnto it, not a ſtone hath beene left vpon a ſtone, but the poore Inhabitants and dwellers thereabout, are vtterly vndone, being depriued of all their ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Prayſed be the diuine Maieſtie for euer, and mought hee be pleaſed to appeaſe his anger, that ſo this puniſhment may ſerue for a warning to all ſinners, and ſo procure vnto vs the amendment of our liues.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>catastrophic flood in Span</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>In the Citie of <hi>Barcelona</hi> the third day of the Month of <hi>Nouember,</hi> in the ſea, and port of the Citie, happened ſuch a ſtorme and tempeſt, that the like hath not beene ſeene
<pb facs="tcp:27027:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27027:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27027:8"/>
in the memory of man. Scarce remayned there a Veſſell on the water, which was not at leaſt leaky and ſorely beaten: the ſhrikes and cryes of the afflicted Mariners, made the moſt dolefull noyſe in the world, and might haue ſoftned and moued to compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the moſt hardened flinty heart. For ſo high and furious was the winde from the Leuante, that neuer was there ſeene ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and dreadfull a ſtorme; the prayers and ſupplications of the diſtreſſed Mariners and other deuont people (for now all <hi>Barcelona</hi> was come together) cauſed a great terrour to all. Some cryed out and called for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon our Lord God Chriſt Jeſus, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocated<note n="b" place="margin">Why is not Chriſt ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, as for the reſt you robbe him of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſo that it may iuſtly bee demaunded of you, <hi>Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired theſe things at your hands?</hi>
               </note> his moſt pittifull Mother the holy Virgin of <hi>Montſerrat,</hi> all prayed and called vpon Saint <hi>Telmo,</hi> and the glorious Saint <hi>Eulalia,</hi> and Saint <hi>Matrona,</hi> the Patroneſſes of <hi>Barcelona.</hi> All the Cleargy of the ſaid Citie came out in Proceſſion, bringing forth the moſt holy Sacrament with them, which they held two and twenty houres vpon the Bulwarke. All the Conuents alſo in the
<pb facs="tcp:27027:8"/>
Towne came forth with very deuout Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions,<note place="margin">Loe here the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge of ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous people.</note> and carryed many Reliques of Saints, which cauſed a wonderfull great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion in all the people. They brought alſo the moſt holy<note n="c" place="margin">As you ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly do beleeue.</note> true Croſſe to the Sea ſide, which they dipt three times in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vntill it pleaſed the diuine Maieſtie to be appeaſed, which was about midnight, this fearefull ſtorme hauing now endured ſixe and twenty houres, and that in ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie, that it caſt a great fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re vpon all the people of <hi>Barcelona:</hi> for it had now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually rained for the ſpace of more then thirty dayes together without intermiſſion, whereupon there ſucceeded ſuch a floud from the Riuer <hi>Lobregat,</hi> and that with ſuch exceſſe and fury, that it carryed away the greateſt part of the houſes and manſions, with two and twenty turrets or ſmall houſes which ſtood on the Riuers ſide, and foure thouſand head of cattell were drowned in this floud, which were found in the vallies and lower grounds, but the greateſt loſſe which this floud cauſed was in Sheepe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27027:9"/>In <hi>Lerida</hi> alſo the freſh or land-floud which came from the Riuer <hi>Segre,</hi> was as violent as the reſt, not to ſpeake of the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite harme which it wrought vpon the lands and houſes of ſuch as liued neare the bankes of this Riuer, that which is moſt<note n="d" place="margin">Thinke vpon it ſeriouſly, and you ſhall finde that al this was not without cauſe</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable was, how in the Citie of <hi>Lerida</hi> theſe waters ſwept quite away a whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent of <hi>Trinitarian Friers,</hi> not leauing any the leaſt ſigne of it behinde: they carryed away alſo the greateſt part of another Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent of <hi>Auguſtine Friers,</hi> and almoſt all the houſes of the Suburbs. To be ſhort, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue beene the harmes alſo which theſe flouds and extraordinary riſings of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter haue done in the kingdom of <hi>Catalumna,</hi> that the vnderſtanding of man cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine them. Moreouer, beſides thoſe many houſes which theſe Riuers haue carryed away, a great number more of houſes haue beene ouerthrowne and caſt to the ground by the violence and extremitie of thoſe thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dayes continuall tempeſts, and vnceſſant great raine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27027:9"/>The Riuer of <hi>Cinca</hi> alſo hath done migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty harme in the fields and townes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about by its extraordinary ſwelling and flowing ouer the bankes.</p>
            <p>God grant that theſe chaſtiſements and warnings which hee giues vs, may cauſe vs to caſt from vs all vices, that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward wee may ſerue him with more truth and ſinceritie, that ſo his holy name may be praiſed for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:27027:10"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>catastrophic flood in Span</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:27027:10"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
